<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>rasta.online</title>
    <description>Interested in creating websites and internet technologies, open-source and team-management ? Browse our the educational articles and tutorials.</description>
    <link>https://rasta.online/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://rasta.online/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 17:02:40 +0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 17:02:40 +0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>JAM Day 1 - Content Management, Products &amp; Categories</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On Day 1 of our JAMstack journey we explore working with &lt;strong&gt;Products&lt;/strong&gt; and compare the CMS options &lt;strong&gt;Forestry&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Netlify CMS&lt;/strong&gt; with a bareback setup which skips the CMS altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To gather experience on which route to take I decided to spin up 3 vanilla Instances with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stackbit.com/&quot; title=&quot;Bundles your JAM Stack&quot;&gt;StackBit&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/snipcart/stackbit-theme-planty/&quot; title=&quot;Planty theme on github&quot;&gt;Planty theme&lt;/a&gt;, the first with &lt;a href=&quot;https://forestry.io/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Forestry&lt;/a&gt;, the second with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlifycms.org/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Netlify CMS&lt;/a&gt; and the last without CMS, relying on the ability to push into a repo myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set myself a couple of tasks to figure out if i can do the job for me and my requirements or not. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/snipcart/stackbit-theme-planty/&quot; title=&quot;Planty theme on github&quot;&gt;Planty theme&lt;/a&gt; comes with dummy products and category collections, so we can get our hands dirty immediately.
I want to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a) be able to manage all existing content (&lt;em&gt;editing, deleting, moving, renaming&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;b) access all files I’ll may need, let’s say &lt;em&gt;.sass&lt;/em&gt; files, &lt;em&gt;includes&lt;/em&gt; and images&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;c) create a new &lt;em&gt;Product&lt;/em&gt; and assign it to a &lt;em&gt;Category&lt;/em&gt; , so it will show in the shop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;d) create new &lt;em&gt;Categories&lt;/em&gt;, assign products and show these products in a new &lt;em&gt;category collection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;content-management-vs-forestry-cms&quot;&gt;Content Management vs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://forestry.io/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Forestry&lt;/a&gt; CMS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forestry.io/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Forestry&lt;/a&gt; seem to be the most popular option, so I started here. After the registration process it was up and running in a few minutes. I logged in and the look and feel of it is nice, surely something you can present to an average customer as suitable UI. The navigation is kept simple and through clicking around you are getting pretty fast a good idea what to find where. For many uses this is indeed a proper solution if your project is in need of web-based UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are drawbacks though, which led me to the conclusion &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to use it. The first thing I noticed that the response of saving content until deployed could take several minutes. Every time when you save something, a commit goes to your connected repo, a build is queued and finally executed. In the free plan is the queue rather fast filled and that can have a serious effect on your work efficiency. This is by no means a deal breaker for me, but the &lt;em&gt;Category management&lt;/em&gt; was. To do tasks &lt;em&gt;a)-c)&lt;/em&gt; was easy, then I ran into a wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to create new Categories, but not to assign them to any product. The form fields in the CMS where not updated, even after triggering additional builds to regenerate the cached config files. I was able to come up with a solution which updates the cache of the form fields, but I spend at least an hour figuring out what was going on and come up with a working fix in the build. This issue was rather frustrating and I hoped avoid it by using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlifycms.org/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Netlify CMS&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;content-management-vs-netlify-cms&quot;&gt;Content Management vs &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlifycms.org/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Netlify CMS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlifycms.org/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Netlify CMS&lt;/a&gt; was the second option as CMS with my chosen Theme. The UI is less pretty then Forestry but will get the job done and is decent enough. Tasks &lt;em&gt;a)-c)&lt;/em&gt; are no problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually the form fields here allowed you to have access to nested properties, which are not exposed through its competitor. This gives you a greater access and control over your content but comes at the cost of cluttering up the space and ease of use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlifycms.org/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Netlify CMS&lt;/a&gt; is a no-nonsense approach which seems mostly suited for managing complex content types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very keen to see what happens when I create a new Category and if it is possible to assign it to the products … nope … exactly the same issue. To investigate and fix the issue I actually had to pull, edit and push the Repo changes back, working with favorite Editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion--no-cms&quot;&gt;Conclusion … No CMS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a moment when I realized that the CMS approach is not the way to go for me. I had to spend more time and energy to fix minor CMS related issues then on solving the tasks of building up any Ecommerce content. A CMS in this context is nothing more then a web-based file editor, which commits into a github repository to save changes. Those commit messages don’t hold any information what was changed, so to roll back to any given point in the history you’ll need to find the correct commit by looking through all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a comfortable Editor setup on my computer and I’m fully able and willing to use github directly and write meaningful commit messages every time I want to push changes. There is nothing I’m not able to do, even more I can do it more comfortable and work faster, since I just rely on my local builds to see changes instead of waiting for my build to be processed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also used to tag and release certain states of my work, to define stable versions and give easy access to rollback points. This is in my normal workflow and a feature I don’t want to miss. I prefer to work with my established developer tools and save the overhead of a CMS at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-next&quot;&gt;What is next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next article we will have a look at how to customize Products to our needs, using custom currencies and be available in multiple languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2019 13:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2019/12/16/day-1-cms-products-categories.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2019/12/16/day-1-cms-products-categories.html</guid>
        
        <category>internet</category>
        
        <category>jam</category>
        
        
        <category>education</category>
        
        <category>software-development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>JAM Day 0 - What are we going to do?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After reading a couple of articles about the current developments in the &lt;strong&gt;JAM&lt;/strong&gt; Stack (&lt;strong&gt;J&lt;/strong&gt;avascript, &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;PI, &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;arkdown) I got really excited about getting my hands dirty and build a little project. Since the usual tutorials often lack the requirements of real-world applications I got the idea of creating an functional online shop, utilizing shiny new tools as &lt;strong&gt;StackBit&lt;/strong&gt; which are available for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My target will be to spend the lowest amount of money and time while building a custom branded, fully operational, automatic deployable shop which is suitable for startup and small business purpose, but extendable for future growth. 
But first things first, lets make a battle plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;objective-herbal-tea-shop&quot;&gt;Objective: Herbal Tea Shop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me and my family like a rather natural diet, we avoid processed foods and enjoy quite a variety of herbal teas. Over the years we gained our experiences and now entertain the idea for a little side-hustle of promoting and selling those teas online. This is an experiment with a rather big chance of failing, so we aim low in regards of investments and just give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we are going to make real money we will be able to manage our products, prices and customers with familiar office tools, so we are not looking for any warehouse management or CRM solution, we just want to present the products and give the buyers an option to order. Neither will we start out with employees, so even user permission management is not an important concern in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will need to make the site multilingual though and provide prices in different currencies as essential part of our marketing strategy, so it will be more complicated as a plain vanilla tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-tools&quot;&gt;The Tools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/em&gt; This is not a paid promotion of any of the following services, I just want to show what I use for my particular project and which experiences I’m going to have with each. In the basic level all tools are free, if I hit a wall and need to pay-to-play I will state that very clearly and look for an alternative solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stackbit&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stackbit.com/&quot; title=&quot;Bundles your JAM Stack&quot;&gt;StackBit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stackbit.com/&quot; title=&quot;Bundles your JAM Stack&quot;&gt;StackBit&lt;/a&gt; will be the backbone for our new shop. It is a very easy and fast way to bundle all the JAM Stack in one UI and bootstrap a new website literally in minutes. It gives you the option to use a pre-build or any custom themes, let you choose your &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;tatic &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;ite &lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;enerator and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content_management_system&quot; title=&quot;Content Management System&quot;&gt;CMS&lt;/a&gt;. The code and data will live in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;Mange your code repositories&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; repository and deployed with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com/&quot; title=&quot;Continuous deployment and serverless functions&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tool has a sleek dashboard which allows you to create and manage your &lt;strong&gt;JAM&lt;/strong&gt; projects. It will do the work of wiring the components together without any complicated integrations and provides you with the links and API key you may need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started registering with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Solomonic&quot; title=&quot;Solomonic&quot;&gt;my GitHub account&lt;/a&gt; and gave &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stackbit.com/&quot; title=&quot;Bundles your JAM Stack&quot;&gt;StackBit&lt;/a&gt; the required authorizations and was on my way of creating my project by pressing the &lt;strong&gt;+ New Project&lt;/strong&gt; button, easy as cake so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;theming&quot;&gt;Theming&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First you are required to choose one from a list of currently ten professional looking themes or adding a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;Mange your code repositories&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; link to a custom theme. You have a &lt;strong&gt;Live Preview&lt;/strong&gt; for each theme and for blogging, a portfolio, documentation or most other purposes is the selection already reasonably well. This step also shows a preview of over 20 upcoming themes which you can’t select yet but gets you and idea what is planned for the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;em&gt;Vanilla theme&lt;/em&gt; as well which is most likely the best starting point if you want to make a fully customer specific theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;custom-planty-theme&quot;&gt;Custom &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/snipcart/stackbit-theme-planty/&quot; title=&quot;Planty theme on github&quot;&gt;Planty theme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t find anything shop like though, so I explored the &lt;strong&gt;Custom Theme&lt;/strong&gt; option and searched the web for JAMstack themes.
I found the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/snipcart/stackbit-theme-planty/&quot; title=&quot;Planty theme on github&quot;&gt;Planty theme&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://snipcart.com/&quot; title=&quot;Javascript based Shopping cart solution&quot;&gt;SnipCart&lt;/a&gt;. The theme looks nice and is ready for getting integrated with a JavaScript based Shopping Cart. In the ReadMe of the repository  is a shiny &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.stackbit.com/create?theme=https://github.com/snipcart/stackbit-theme-planty&amp;amp;ssg=jekyll&quot; title=&quot;Create a new project with Planty Theme&quot;&gt;Create with StackBit&lt;/a&gt; button which creates a new project in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stackbit.com/&quot; title=&quot;Bundles your JAM Stack&quot;&gt;StackBit&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/snipcart/stackbit-theme-planty/&quot; title=&quot;Planty theme on github&quot;&gt;Planty theme&lt;/a&gt; already set as the custom theme. Here you also can clear this theme-URL and add your own repository-URL or paste the StackBit sample repo if you just want to explore how to make custom themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;site-generator&quot;&gt;Site Generator&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next step you have to choose your site generator. Currently you have the options of &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; title=&quot;Static Site Generator working with github pages&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gohugo.io/&quot; title=&quot;Super Fast Go based Static Site Generator&quot;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gatsbyjs.org/&quot; title=&quot;JavaScript based Static Site Generator for React&quot;&gt;Gatsby&lt;/a&gt;, while more options like VuePress and Hexo are already announced. I’ve choosen &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; title=&quot;Static Site Generator working with github pages&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, I like that it also can run with &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;GitHub hosted Pages&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; and it is the one I have the most experience with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continue to CMS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cms&quot;&gt;CMS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we can currently choose between 6 Options: &lt;a href=&quot;https://forestry.io/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Forestry&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlifycms.org/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Netlify CMS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Contentful&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;DatoCMS&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Sanity&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;No CMS&lt;/strong&gt;.
My &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/snipcart/stackbit-theme-planty/&quot; title=&quot;Planty theme on github&quot;&gt;Planty theme&lt;/a&gt; supports &lt;a href=&quot;https://forestry.io/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Forestry&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlifycms.org/&quot; title=&quot;Static Content CMS&quot;&gt;Netlify CMS&lt;/a&gt; but since I actually don’t know either, I want to test them out first and choose &lt;strong&gt;No CMS&lt;/strong&gt; for now. Anyway, since I try to understand how the content flow actually works I figure its a good option to work without it first and add it manually later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;repository&quot;&gt;Repository&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently the &lt;strong&gt;repository&lt;/strong&gt; with the website data has to be on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;Mange your code repositories&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, GitLab and Bitbucket Integrations are announced though. Since this would be my first choice anyway I’m good with that and move on to Deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;deployment&quot;&gt;Deployment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deployments are right now just done with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com/&quot; title=&quot;Continuous deployment and serverless functions&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt;. I just created a free account with my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;Mange your code repositories&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; login, authorized it and seem to be good to go. &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;GitHub hosted Pages&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;GitLab Pages&lt;/strong&gt; are announced but for now we’ll see how well &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com/&quot; title=&quot;Continuous deployment and serverless functions&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; does the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;connect-accounts&quot;&gt;Connect Accounts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all I have to enter a name for the project and I call it &lt;strong&gt;Rasta-Herb-Teas&lt;/strong&gt; and then connect it to my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;Mange your code repositories&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; account. A few clicks later everything seems to be alright. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stackbit.com/&quot; title=&quot;Bundles your JAM Stack&quot;&gt;StackBit&lt;/a&gt; will now create a &lt;em&gt;public&lt;/em&gt; repository with the name &lt;strong&gt;rasta-herb-teas&lt;/strong&gt; for my user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;create-project&quot;&gt;Create project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a message that my site is currently deploying and less then 2 Minutes later	I got the notification of success. My site is now live available at &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;https://rasta-herb-teas-BUILD_ID.netlify.com/&lt;/code&gt;, this link can be shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I follow the link I see indeed a working site build with my template, plus a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stackbit.com/&quot; title=&quot;Bundles your JAM Stack&quot;&gt;StackBit&lt;/a&gt; management overlay that allows me to rebuild from here or go directly to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com/&quot; title=&quot;Continuous deployment and serverless functions&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; project or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;Mange your code repositories&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; repository. That’s neat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual creation process of bootstrapping a working website with a selected theme and dummy content takes indeed just a few minutes and can be done even from a mobile phone without a problem. After all it’s just choose and click, the only typing are your password and project name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the very first project it took me clearly longer since I had to register and authorize the components. I spend by far the most time choosing a template but it felt self-explanatory all the time. Until now &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stackbit.com/&quot; title=&quot;Bundles your JAM Stack&quot;&gt;StackBit&lt;/a&gt; gets a clear thumbs up, it did what it promised and looked good while doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can spin up a fresh professional prototype which is online available while talking with a customer. This allows you to get into the specific details in the very first meeting and is the easiest and fastest bootstrapping I’ve seen so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;Whats next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article just aimed to outline the project and tools. In the follow up I want to apply a branding and work with the products, so it already get the looks and feels of a real shop. I strive to find a strategy how to deal with multilingual contents and try to figure out which CMS best fits my needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2019 13:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2019/11/09/day-0-defining-the-goals-for-jam-ecommerce.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2019/11/09/day-0-defining-the-goals-for-jam-ecommerce.html</guid>
        
        <category>internet</category>
        
        <category>jam</category>
        
        
        <category>education</category>
        
        <category>software-development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Problems with the facebook share? The wrong text or image shows up?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Every CMS offers widgets and helpers to share your blog/website in popular social networks as facebook. To get the share-button in is usually very easy but a bad surprise often follows when we see which content and image shows up (or not) in facebooks share dialog. We will have a quick look at the basics of open graph parameters and how they need to be included to in the website or blog. Once this is set, we will use the facebook debugger tool to ensure we get the latest content included and we are happy with the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not sure what I’m talking about, just &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.com/sharer.php?u=https://Rasta.Online/education/software-development/2015/12/11/facebook-share-dialog-and-open-graph-meta-tags.html&quot; title=&quot;Open facebook share diaog...&quot;&gt;open the share dialog here&lt;/a&gt;. You will see a preview image of this article, the article description and authorship. This article deals with problems in this dialog. The information displayed there are part of your websites&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and need to be set correctly to produce good resuls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the informations set, we may still don’t see the correct text and even more often no or a wrong image. The reason is that facebook reads these information only the first time anybody shares a page, saves it and from now serves these cached information to any new share, even so when our websites is updated with a new image and description. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.facebook.com/tools/debug/og/object/&quot; title=&quot;Open debugger tool ...&quot;&gt;Open Graph Object Debugger&lt;/a&gt; allows us to clear this saved results and use the latest data instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;check-your-head&quot;&gt;Check your HEAD&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use a CMS as Wordpress, Joomla!, Drupal, Typo3 or Plone the social-share addon of choice is suppossed to do this and we just need to check if everything is in place. If you &lt;a href=&quot;/https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/11/19/faster-cheaper-safer.html&quot; title=&quot;Read more about Jekyll and static site generators ...&quot;&gt;use a static site generator&lt;/a&gt; or simple static html, you easily can include these meta-tags by yourself. You want to inspect the website source code (&lt;em&gt;right click&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;view source&lt;/em&gt; ) and search for the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      ...
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;Search&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;these&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;tags&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:title&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;The main title for our post&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:image&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;absolute URL to the image shown with the share&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:description&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;The description is the long text in the share dialog, explaining your visitors what they can get in your blog.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:site_name&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;The name of your site or something catchy&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:url&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;URL: this article&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:type&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;website or article?&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:locale&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Language Code&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Author info --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;article:author&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;URL: facebook user or page&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;article:publisher&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;URL: facebook user or page&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- End --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    ...
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.com/sharer.php?u=https://Rasta.Online/education/software-development/2015/12/11/facebook-share-dialog-and-open-graph-meta-tags.html&quot;&gt;the share dialog&lt;/a&gt; with this articles settings and it should get clear what each tag is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      ...
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;Search&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;these&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;tags&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:title&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Problems with the facebook share? The wrong text or image shows up?&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:image&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;http://rasta.online/library/images/facebook-share.jpg&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:description&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;This article explains how to set all needed information in open graph tags of your website and how to use the debugger tools to get the latest results.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:site_name&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Duppy conqueror in the digital jungle.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:url&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;https://Rasta.Online/education/software-development/2015/12/11/facebook-share-dialog-and-open-graph-meta-tags.html&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:type&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;article&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;og:locale&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;en_US&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Author info --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;article:author&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;property=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;article:publisher&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;content=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- End --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      ...
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make sure that these meta-tags with the properties &lt;em&gt;og:title&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;og:description&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;og:image&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;og:site_name&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;og:url&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;og:type&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;og:locale&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;article:author&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;article:publisher&lt;/em&gt; are included &lt;strong&gt;exactly once&lt;/strong&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/em&gt;. I’ve seen problems when you have the &lt;em&gt;og:title&lt;/em&gt; or others twice included. On static html websites you simply write these tags direct into your source-code, if you &lt;a href=&quot;/https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/11/19/faster-cheaper-safer.html&quot; title=&quot;Read more about Jekyll and static site generators ...&quot;&gt;use a static site generator&lt;/a&gt; just check &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Solomonic/theming.rasta_online/blob/master/_includes/open_graph.html&quot; title=&quot;Easy Open-graph tags inclusion ...&quot;&gt;this blogs solution&lt;/a&gt;. If you work with a CMS as Wordpress, Joomla, Typo3, Drupal, Django or Plone first look for an addon/extension providing these tags for your system, there are plenty different available. I encountered problems in some Wordpress themes including these tags twice and I had to edit the layout files head.php to make it right. A good theme shouldn’t have the problem, but if you are in the situation and can’t figure it out, &lt;a href=&quot;http://Rasta.Online/contact&quot;&gt;ask for help&lt;/a&gt;. You will need to have control over these tags before you can use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.facebook.com/tools/debug/og/object/&quot; title=&quot;Open debugger tool ...&quot;&gt;Open Graph Object Debugger&lt;/a&gt; in an effective manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-debugger&quot;&gt;The Debugger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook luckily offers a &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.facebook.com/tools/debug/og/object/&quot; title=&quot;Open Graph Debugger&quot;&gt;free developer tool&lt;/a&gt; to debug problems with these open-graph meta tags and solve the caching problem. We need to have a facebook account to use it so if you have none, create it for development purpose and use a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trash-mail.com/en/&quot; title=&quot;Disposable email service with all conventional mailbox functions!&quot;&gt;disposable email service&lt;/a&gt; for privacy protection. Once you are logged in are we ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you have the debugger open now&lt;/strong&gt; just paste the URL of you website/blog in the input field and click the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fetch new scrape Information&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As result are we getting a page with all the &lt;strong&gt;latest&lt;/strong&gt; data. Just scroll down and you will see errors if any, which tags were found and a preview of the share dialog. It’s a good time now to phrase an attractive descriptions for your content and to play around to find an nice image. What you need to know about the picture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the minimum-size is 200 x 200px, everything &lt;strong&gt;smaller is ignored&lt;/strong&gt; and the next big image is used instead.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for big image effect: use picture of &lt;strong&gt;1200 x 630px&lt;/strong&gt; or bigger for high resolution devices or at least 600 x 315px&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to avoid unwanted cropping of the image, try a &lt;strong&gt;ratio close to 1.91:1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to check each post one by one, to ensure the correct images and text is showing. I for example had an issue, that the image used on &lt;em&gt;http://Rasta.Online/about&lt;/em&gt; was not updated besides the fact that the path was correct, the image well sized and available through the web. I &lt;strong&gt;fetched new scrape information&lt;/strong&gt; couple of times but with no change. Finally I tried &lt;em&gt;http://Rasta.Online/about&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;/&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and I got the updated results, everything works now fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Graph tags are often treated as &lt;em&gt;“this facebook thing”&lt;/em&gt; because it is the most common usecase. I see today a fast growing amount of other tools, also using these tags to generate previews in chats and messaging apps. So we don’t do this for facebook, we do it for a more user-friendly internet. Find out more about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ogp.me/&quot; title=&quot;More about the Open Graph protocol ...&quot;&gt;Open Graph protocol&lt;/a&gt;, and its possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stay tuned&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2015 13:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/12/11/facebook-share-dialog-and-open-graph-meta-tags.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/12/11/facebook-share-dialog-and-open-graph-meta-tags.html</guid>
        
        <category>internet</category>
        
        
        <category>education</category>
        
        <category>software-development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Free software tools for your success</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We are going to introduce a software strategy for a fictional brand called FantasticContent.Online to demonstrate how different free tools can be combined to a rock solid base for many kinds business relying on teamwork. We will not be limited to a certain product, but want to have a look on aspects surrounding successful projects. We will see how to organize teams flexible, build short communications and make the life easy for the business and marketeers. Ready? Let’s go ….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the third part of a series of educational articles, covering existing web-technologies with the aim to encourage smarter, faster and cheaper solutions for different kinds of online projects.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-company&quot;&gt;The Company&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to FantasticContent.Online, the global acting cooperation of creators struggling to build a business without a dime in the pocket. We produce digital distributable content as videos, music, games or apps and use established channels to reach our customers. Maybe we produce content for video-portals, write articles for online-news, upload our music into cloud-streaming or create an Android app. No matter what we do, the competition is hard but we come prepared, are motivated and our creators have loads of talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our business goal is to gain a fan-base and convert a part of it into paying customers. We prefer free access to our content-products to reach the widest possible range of viewers/listeners/users, encouraging to share and publish under the CreativeCommon License. We want to be on the right side of history, so we don’t team up with copyright bullies and actually want to give something back to the community. We have no heavy advertisement budget available, so we will use social engagement to gain positive attention and motivate others to support us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FantasticContent.Online is the brand and website we are going to establish besides our content distribution-channel. This will enable us to build up a community of supporters, sell special services or merchandise and promote events. The website alone will not drive the business in the beginning but is a point of reference and adds credibility. Therefor are we going for a cheap solution first, adding features as needed in the process when we are able to invest profits. We assume that smartphones soon will be the top amount of devices to serve our website, followed by tablets, laptops, desktops and gaming consoles. We want one fitting solution for all devices and indexes in the best possible manner in all search engines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-teams&quot;&gt;The teams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;communications-and-cooperation&quot;&gt;Communications and cooperation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scrum_(software_development)&quot;&gt;Scrum&lt;/a&gt; is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agile_software_development&quot;&gt;agile software development&lt;/a&gt; process or a way of organizing teamwork to increase productivity, quality and to react &lt;em&gt;agile&lt;/em&gt; on changing requirements. Scrum usually utilizes daily 15min stand-up meetings where all team members tell the rest of the team what 1) they have done yesterday 2) what they are they going to do today 3) Are problems in sight? &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.agilemanifesto.org&quot; title=&quot;Read the agile manifesto ...&quot;&gt;The agile principles&lt;/a&gt; where often presented as the only right approach for any project, but my professional experience does not support this as truth and neither so for many of my colleague as &lt;a href=&quot;http://opensource.com/business/15/11/open-development-method&quot; title=&quot;Read full article: Scrum is dead: breaking down the new open development method &quot;&gt;the excellent article&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;http://opensource.com/users/ahmadnassri&quot;&gt;Ahmad Nassri&lt;/a&gt; shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our setup will rather consider decentralized team-members working asynchron from different locations and timezones, then a well organized team in a shared office. So Scrum is not really fitting, but anyway are some of its tools very useful for supporting global teamwork as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban&quot; title=&quot;read about Kanban on wikipedia ....&quot;&gt;Kanban&lt;/a&gt; boards on &lt;a href=&quot;http://trello.com&quot; title=&quot;Work together on task lists ...&quot;&gt;trello.com&lt;/a&gt; for coordinating tasks and organizing projects of any size. A classic &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban&quot; title=&quot;read about Kanban on wikipedia ....&quot;&gt;Kanban&lt;/a&gt; board actually contains three lists, one for open tasks-to-do, one for tasks the team is working on right now and one for the finished tasks. Each task is named and described on a card, it can contain attachments as images, can have a date, can be commented and rated by team members and is flexible to organize with colored labels. Team members updating these tasks status by moving cards between the lists and notifications where sent out. This visualization helps a lot to see whats going on in a team, shortens communication lines and enables team-leaders to balance work load and identify problems early. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://trello.com&quot; title=&quot;Work together on task lists ...&quot;&gt;free online tool&lt;/a&gt; offers &lt;a href=&quot;https://trello.com/tour&quot;&gt;a lot useful features&lt;/a&gt; as real-time notification, filters, time-lines, access-management and unlimited team members cooperating on one board for one goal. Nevertheless is it well received by people with little technical understanding because … it is fun to use and implements a good UX strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The center piece of our team communication is a messaging app and amazing tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://slack.com/is&quot; title=&quot;Get convinced by #slack...&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;, this will replace emails for us and give our teamwork some slickness, transparency and efficiency. Slack allows teams to create unlimited amounts of &lt;strong&gt;#channels&lt;/strong&gt; and send direct messages to them. A channel can represent a certain topic, a project or department and collects all related communication in the same place. We can have open channels which each team member can join and read all older messages or private channels which allow only invited members for confidential topics. All communications are searchable as well as the shared files, this is extremly useful if a new team members needs to get instructed into an ongoing project or if you just forgot what the customer actually wanted. Slack also allows to integrate our Social Networks for the marketing, updates on the Cloud hosting for the Content Creators, Github for the techies as well as the Hangout for video calls. There are free and native apps for Mac, Windows and Linux as well as the mobile versions for iOS, Android and Windows Phone. The feature-set is pretty neat and can be upgraded later by a payed version once we made money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our team members need to share big hunks of data, like raw video material, huge audio files or high resolution photographs, we actually have the choice between many &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_storage&quot; title=&quot;What is cloud storage?&quot;&gt;cloud storage&lt;/a&gt; providers with free options. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/&quot; title=&quot;Visit Dropbox website ...&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most used services which offers 2-3GB for free and integrates very well with other tools as &lt;a href=&quot;https://slack.com/is&quot; title=&quot;Visit #slack website ...&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://onedrive.live.com/&quot;&gt;Microsoft OneDrive&lt;/a&gt; just slashed the free unlimited storage option down to 5GB. I think this is quite a drastic move which will have heavy effect on the popularity and acceptance of Microsofts service. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/drive/&quot; title=&quot;Visit GoogleDrive Website ...&quot;&gt;GoogleDrive&lt;/a&gt; comes with a 15GB free account with each Gmail email address and also offers a high variety of integrations in any tools our teams may use. A very interesting offer is coming from &lt;a href=&quot;https://mega.co.nz/&quot; title=&quot;Visit Mega website ...&quot;&gt;Mega&lt;/a&gt;, offering 50GB for free and &lt;strong&gt;encryption&lt;/strong&gt;, so nobody outside the team, including Mega itself, can read the stored data. The offer is solid and would be my personal choice. We won’t consider Apples ICloud since it is to limiting for our team setup, not everybody wants to use Apple products. There are other services gaining more attention as &lt;a href=&quot;https://tresorit.com/&quot; title=&quot;Visit Tresorit&quot;&gt;tresorit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcloud.com/&quot; title=&quot;Visit pCloud website&quot;&gt;pCloud&lt;/a&gt;, so we should keep an eye on them before we assemble our storage solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the knowledge how to manage the teams, ease communication and offering &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_storage&quot; title=&quot;What is cloud storage?&quot;&gt;cloud based storage&lt;/a&gt; we have everything in place to have a look at the teams itself. A team in this context is a role or a list of responsibilities, helping to visualize the different kinds of tasks in a company. A team can have any size and always should be open to flexible changes. Real people doing the real work are often in different teams,
common combinations are Content Creators &amp;amp; Marketing or Techies and SEO strategies. We will need at least 2 people to make FantasticContent.Online real so let’s have a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;team-techies&quot;&gt;Team Techies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The odds are pretty good that the techie team is yourself, you found your way here and kept reading. Let’s talk then Rasta.
We will go for simple solutions, so there is no engineering degree needed, just curiousity and the wish to find and combine the most useful tools around. The work of this team starts with the initial setups of all tools, prepare and test the workflows and to introduce these to other teams. Many of us hate to write documentations, trust me it’s still better to write it one time down instead of explaining the same thing over and over again and get complains from Creators and Business. Once the setup is done, your life will become very easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basis of FantasticContent.Online brand will be a website we are going to build with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs&quot; title=&quot;Visit the Jekyll documentation ...&quot;&gt;Jekyll framework&lt;/a&gt; which I already discussed in the &lt;a href=&quot;/https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/11/19/faster-cheaper-safer.html&quot; title=&quot;Read the previous article ...&quot;&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; of this series. It allows us to use the hosting service of &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;, which actually outsources all our server-troubles for free. No need for server- or security-updates, no wories about broken hardware and backup-safety on highest standard, FantasticContent.Online will take this deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An other big advantage of &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; is that it allows us to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot; title=&quot;Visit github.com ...&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Repository_(version_control)&quot; title=&quot;What is a software repository?&quot;&gt;Repositories&lt;/a&gt; as a through-the-web backend for our website, including sophisticated user-right management and real-time updates on the website without any 3rd party software. We can log into github, edit files, push them and the changes are imediatly online. So even the compiling is outsourced, so hardware is mainly used for reading and writing on websites. If you build your own PC please &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/?q=unix+like+os&amp;amp;t=ffab&amp;amp;ia=about&quot; title=&quot;Good and free ...&quot;&gt;use a Operating System that supports you&lt;/a&gt; instead of Windows, a Mac will also do the job any day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once our prototyping reaches a state where we start to include non-techies for creating and managing content, we will need to have clear defined release steps, which are easy to follow but prevent that someone by accident breaks the website. The best strategy will vary, depending on team skills, update frequency, amount of members and content type. The Creators can work in a cloned/forked repository with the very own &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; hosted domain to preview the changes. Done and ready they send a pull request to the techie responsible for releases, the technical quality control and the merge to the live site. This is a flexible approach which could handle big teams with high production rates but seems also reasonable in small setups with very view team members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a developer I still will prefer to run Jekyll on my localhost, have direct access to error messages and use my very own tools for editing and version control. Other people will do something else and that is a freedom I’ve seen with no CMS so far. Content can be accessed with most different tools now, adaptable and open to whatever is needed and whatever clever comes up next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The techies are usually also responsible that the website have the right setup to get indexed well in search engines. We will use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/webmasters/&quot; title=&quot;Find a good SEO setup, identify&amp;amp; fix problems for search engines ...&quot;&gt;Google Webmaster Tools&lt;/a&gt; to to test our SEO setup and always keep an eye on new problems or improvements. SEO need to be part of our prototype and is mainly done with a set of &lt;em&gt;META&lt;/em&gt; data in the websites &lt;em&gt;HEAD&lt;/em&gt;, providing a &lt;em&gt;unique&lt;/em&gt; title, description, … for each article. Creators need to write extra descriptions for the search results, directed to human readers, providing a good, short and understandable summary what to expect from each article. There are many &lt;em&gt;SEO Experts&lt;/em&gt; offering services which are trivial and can be easily done by ourselfes OR using hacks and tricks to increase rankings. Neither one is an option we want, the second is maybe tempting but usually gets punished by the search engine within a quite short time. Keep an eye open for follow ups if you are interested in this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;team-creators&quot;&gt;Team Creators&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Creators are the heart and the soul of any content based business, so we want to allow them to work in the least distracting way. Each Creator should be able to use the most convinient tools to get the work done, the software should support them instead of forcing certain workflows with a narrow set of technologies. Let’s discuss some team setups to see what kind of issues we need to face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team Youtube&lt;/strong&gt; creates funny cat videos and has steady rising subscriber numbers. They are a rapidly growing team gathering material, cutting the clips and uploading it to the video-portal. This team has an existing fanbase but wants to expend over the boundaries of youtube and also publish in other video portals, on facebook or app-based video-shares. FantasticContent.Online will be a website containing references to all videos in the different portals, a stage to present the combined content from different sources under one brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team Musicians &amp;amp; DJ’s&lt;/strong&gt; produce music and mixes and promote them via free streaming as &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/&quot; title=&quot;Discover new tracks and get connected with artists ... soundcloud.com&quot;&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt;. FantasticContent.Online will be a website mainly aimed to promote non-digital events as concerts or shows. We will collect the emails of our fans with a newsletter tool as &lt;a href=&quot;http://mailchimp.com/&quot; title=&quot;Send better Email campaigns with MailChimp.&quot;&gt;MailChimp&lt;/a&gt; and keep them close and interested with regular updates, hoping they are coming and supporting the upcoming events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team Photo &amp;amp; Webdesign&lt;/strong&gt; are visual artists, looking for a way of displaying a portfolio. This team puts by far the most focus on the presentation itself, so potential customer are simply blown away by slickness. This team will need to include skilled webdesigners, able to deliver HTML and CSS files. There is no need for special skills in theming of a CMS, all this team have to deliver is static HTML. The convertion of those static files into the theme can be done with a low effort by the techies, familar with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs&quot; title=&quot;Visit the Jekyll documentation ...&quot;&gt;Jekyll framework&lt;/a&gt;. Our website setup allows the highest control of the Layout with the highest flexibility of content presentation. You can place what you want, exactly where you want, CMS usually don’t allow this without a greater knowledge of the internal theming process. Even as an expert in Plone and Typo3, after dozens of successful projects and teaching huge classes how to use them right and boosting results, I have to admit that there are certain aspects I can’t control in a reasonable manner, including overheads in data-load or the weird behavior of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/TinyMCE&quot; title=&quot;What is a TinyMCE?&quot;&gt;TinyMCE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team Journalist &amp;amp; Blogger&lt;/strong&gt; are writers which use FantasticContent.Online as a channel of exposure. The focus of this team is that articles get indexed in the best possible manner by search-egines and that these results get an inviting presentation. The work of this team also needs to be provided via &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS&quot; title=&quot;What is RSS?&quot;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt; and must be shareable via social networks. I consider this blog in this team. so I will follow up with articles about healthy search-engine gardening, structured content for better search results and what you actually have to know and to do to get this facebook shares right and nice. With our approach is it possible to write and create off-the-grid in areas with no or unstable internet connection and just later push it all online. Creators can write first-hand experience from the wildernis when they are there, instead of remembering things back in a internet-cafe, I guess that can be an real advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team Game &amp;amp; App&lt;/strong&gt; This team have technical skilled members deploying a project page. We like to introduce the features of our product, provide links to the download and include our user- and developer documentations. This team can &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_documentation_generators&quot; title=&quot;What is a documentation generator?&quot;&gt;automate the documentation&lt;/a&gt; and link in the website. Most of these pages today are using simple standardized and full responsive layouts, avoiding big images and therefor long pages-loads. The best way to o that? &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;team-marketing--business&quot;&gt;Team Marketing &amp;amp; Business&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money makes the world go round and it’s also very useful to exchange for goods and services. People can be motivated for a &lt;em&gt;short time&lt;/em&gt; to put a lot of work and energy into projects without payment, amazing things can be done without money but a serious business will need cash to deliver constant &lt;em&gt;professional&lt;/em&gt; results and build sustained teams. The business teams responsibility is to get the bills payed for everyone, so we need full support for all marketing efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;starting-up-&quot;&gt;Starting up …&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crowdfunding&quot; title=&quot;What is crowdfunding?&quot;&gt;Crowdfunding&lt;/a&gt; is in our days one of the most powerful tools for business development. Awesome Creators or Techies are often not qualified or experienced enough to work out a convincing business plan, so help is needed. To use a crowdfunding platform to develop and test a business model is a smart move, it allows direct feedback with an interested audience, we can promote the idea itself and find out what is actually wanted by the community. A failing crowdfunding campaign teaches us a lot and filters out stupid and risky ideas. If we can convince enough people to give FantasticContent.Online money for an non-existing product, then we have a product interesting enough and the first customers right by our hands. And of course we get the money from the campaign which allows us to get serious. In consultations for start-ups I usually recommend to organize and crowdfund projects in several steps. We want to start with a very reasonable first goal and minimal buyable product, in later steps we will react on the feedback of our audience and maybe go in a different directions then what we would expect initially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many platforms for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crowdfunding&quot; title=&quot;What is crowdfunding?&quot;&gt;crowdfunding&lt;/a&gt; available, depending on our project we will need to choose the best one for our cause. The most famous portal is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/&quot; title=&quot;Crowdfunding with Kickstarter&quot;&gt;Kickstarter&lt;/a&gt; with over $200 millions raised and over 60.000 projects launched. FantasticContent.Online is a creative project, so we should be good with its &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kickstarter.com/help/guidelines&quot; title=&quot;Kickstarter project guidelines ...&quot;&gt;guidelines&lt;/a&gt; BUT the campaign creator needs to be a U.S. resident. So we have a look at other options as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiegogo.com/&quot; title=&quot;Crowdfund with IndieGoGo ...&quot;&gt;IndieGoGo&lt;/a&gt;, which don’t restrict us in this manner or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rockethub.com/&quot; title=&quot;Crowdfund with RocketHub ...&quot;&gt;RocketHub&lt;/a&gt; which also offers Creators the &lt;em&gt;Launchpad&lt;/em&gt; feature to promote and raise public interest together with other top brands. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crowdfunder.com/&quot; title=&quot;Crowdfunding with Crowdfunder ...&quot;&gt;Crowdfunder&lt;/a&gt; is targeted to approach &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angel_investor&quot; title=&quot;What is an Agel Investor?&quot;&gt;Angel Investors&lt;/a&gt; and gain &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venture_capital&quot; title=&quot;What is Venture Capital?&quot;&gt;Venture Capital&lt;/a&gt; into the startup. There are more specialist platforms as &lt;a href=&quot;http://index.appbackr.com/&quot; title=&quot;Crowdfunding for Apps ...&quot;&gt;AppBackr&lt;/a&gt; if we produce a mobile App or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sellaband.com/&quot; title=&quot;Where Fans invest in music ...&quot;&gt;SellABand&lt;/a&gt; for musicians. Usually are fees around 5% of the raised amount but the details vary and need to be checked properly before the we go for one portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter which one we choose, there are general rules which we need to implement. We will need to &lt;strong&gt;start early&lt;/strong&gt; to work on our campaign, at least a couple of month &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt; we launch it. We will promote our idea, collect email addresses and get the word out in the communities we identified as our target group. We don’t need to please everybody, usually are less then 1.000 backers needed, so we can focus in a certain direction. We will &lt;strong&gt;do our homework&lt;/strong&gt; and research similar campaigns on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/&quot; title=&quot;Data on Kickstarter&quot;&gt;Kickstarter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiegogo.com/&quot; title=&quot;Data on IndieGoGo ...&quot;&gt;IndieGoGo&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a very good start to do some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_analysis&quot;&gt;Data analysis&lt;/a&gt; and compare successful and unsuccessful campaigns to identify good and bad approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to have an inviting campaign, so we will &lt;strong&gt;set the lowest possible donation amount&lt;/strong&gt; to $1 and reward donors on multiple investment levels. Investors need to get more then a thank-you email, so each will get discounted prices for our services and we will give out extra rewards for donations worth $5, $10, $20, $50, $100, $500, $1000. These rewards are one of the main determining factors for the campaign, so spend some time and come up with some GOOD ideas. We will not spend much money on those but they need to be attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will set our campaigns funding goal as low as we can affort to make a success more likely. If a goal is not reached, we don’t get anything. If we get more donations then defined in the goal, then we just get more money. So we take our costs, add the fee’s of the portal and payment provider but no profit margin. Now is the time to get the project started, later on is the time for profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor we will not underestimate is the presentation of our campaign and its support. We will provide a professional layout for the campaign on the portal and also a free mini-website for the campaign itself. The &lt;strong&gt;data shows that presentation matters&lt;/strong&gt;, so let’s spend some hours and make it nice and neat. We also want to have at least 3 different videos to promote our cause. The first will be used before the campaign starts to gather interest, spread the word and invite people to follow our news. The second video will be promoted while the campaign is on, encouraging people to donate. The third video is the final thanks to the donors, if any. If it’s reasonable we don’t skip the last one even if the campaign failed. A failed campaign just means we need to work on a new and better one, so we will treat all donors very nicely and try to get them on-board later again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;know-your-audience-make-them-customers&quot;&gt;Know your audience, make them customers&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business model of FantasticContent.Online hugely depends on our content, but there are different guidelines we want to follow anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exposure&lt;/strong&gt; in search engines will drive the very most visitors to our website, way more we could reach with any conventional promotion methods. Therefor is the Search Engine Optimization one main pillar of a successful marketing and goes through all departments. The technical background is covered by our techies, business and marketing need to strategize which keywords and phrases should be targeted and the creators need to produce content accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analyze&lt;/strong&gt; the incoming traffic to see what is working and what not. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/analytics/&quot; title=&quot;Visit google analytics ...&quot;&gt;Google analytics&lt;/a&gt; offers an impressive range of features and is for many years now the favorite toolset of most professionals working with website-traffic data. If our marketing is promoting something, we surely want to know which effects we got. By analyzing bounce rates we can find issues in the user experience and improve steady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep in touch&lt;/strong&gt; with vistors. We will promote a Newsletter signup on FantasticContent.Online to send out news, events and promotions. &lt;a href=&quot;http://mailchimp.com/&quot; title=&quot;Visit MailChimp ...&quot;&gt;MailChimp&lt;/a&gt; is currently the best free solution for email marketing and offers sophisticated features as a fancy drag and drop designer, automations and analytics for campaigns and A/B testing. It serves as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Customer_relationship_management&quot; title=&quot;What is CRM?&quot;&gt;CRM&lt;/a&gt; tool and is surprising flexible in its possibilities. I worked with a lot of companies utelizing &lt;a href=&quot;http://mailchimp.com/&quot; title=&quot;Visit MailChimp ...&quot;&gt;MailChimp&lt;/a&gt; in totally different scales and I heard very little complains or problems so far. It is a solid choice since a couple of years and adds interesting options for marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to &lt;strong&gt;build additional revenue streams&lt;/strong&gt; besides our core product. If FantasticContent.Online has a considerable fanbase, this task is actually quite easy. Our fans like to support us, so some will buy our merchandise products and come to our events, that is where we can get the good profits. In the classic non-digital music business is the real money coming from the concert tours, not so much from the sold records. In the age where we can get everything free anyway, this is clearly more true then ever before. Our content itself needs to be free available to reach a maximum of people, extra services and non-digital goods can be charged. This approach works well for each of the software tools mentioned in this article and can be seen as a proven strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a view words to uneffective marketing approaches as classic &lt;strong&gt;banner advertising&lt;/strong&gt;. Ask yourself, when did you actually click the last time on a banner yourself? Most banner ads are blocked away by browser extensions as &lt;a href=&quot;https://adblockplus.org&quot; title=&quot;World famous browser extension blocks all ads away.&quot;&gt;AdBlock Plus&lt;/a&gt; or are simply ignored. To invest money and effort into this is mostly a waste of ressources. It is way better to focus on targeted campaigns in the most popular social media communities, addressing certain groups of interest. People organize themself into groups, so we can use this, find the right circles and get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All tools in this guide seem to be very interesting solutions for a wide range of tasks, actually allowing to build a convinient and professional software base for creative and agile businesses. At the date of posting all the mentioned tools are free to use without time limitations and are tested and used by myself in real-world projects. Not every setup will require every tool, new and better solutions will follow, the idea of this article is to show existing options and opportunities. The follow up articles will shed some light on serveral issues just mentioned quickly here, with more details and practical use-cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned ….&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 13:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/12/08/free-softeware-tools-for-your-online-business-success.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/12/08/free-softeware-tools-for-your-online-business-success.html</guid>
        
        <category>internet</category>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        
        <category>education</category>
        
        <category>software-development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>faster, cheaper, safer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The commonly used CMS (Wordpress, Joomla!, …) are all server-side applications which require sophisticated features from the hosting environment, such as a database and activated PHP or Python compilers. Your website-project is of reasonable size, aimed for exposure, performance, and SEO rather than direct interaction with visitors as in community sites or e-commerce? Then you might not need any paid hosting at all anymore. Sounds good? Let’s dive into pre-compiled websites and what they have to offer …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the second part of a series of educational articles, covering existing web technologies with the aim to encourage smarter, faster and cheaper solutions for small projects. The previous article explained the concept of CMS. Feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;/https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/11/17/cms-wordpress-joomla-drupal-django-typo3-plone.html&quot; title=&quot;Read the previous article&quot;&gt;read it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-new-tool--a-different-kind-of-cms&quot;&gt;The new tool- A different kind of CMS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A CMS is an application, merging together &lt;a href=&quot;/https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/11/17/cms-wordpress-joomla-drupal-django-typo3-plone.html&quot; title=&quot;Read about this in the previous article&quot;&gt;Content data and Layout&lt;/a&gt; into a website. It is not only possible with a huge server-side application. A Web-developer can use a static site generator to compile any complex and nested site-structures from data and configuration files on their own computer (a.k.a. localhost) and upload the resulting static website folder to the host-server. The compiling is not done on the server in real-time. It is done beforehand, and this make all the difference for the hosting requirements and final page speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My weapon of choice is &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/home/&quot; title=&quot;Visit the Jekyll Documentation to learn more&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, so I will focus on its advantages and disadvantages I encountered while using it. &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot; title=&quot;Visit Jekyll website,,&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; already powers very trusted sources such as this blog or &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;Visit GitHub Pages&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; and even allows your project to be hosted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;Visit GitHub Pages&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;, 100% free and direct from a github repository. Anyway, this article will not focus on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/github-pages/&quot; title=&quot;integrate with GitHub Pages&quot;&gt;extra features of one hosting service&lt;/a&gt;. It will discuss the broader possibilies of site-generators using &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; as an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;so-how-does-it-work&quot;&gt;So how does it work?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pre-compiling CMS is actually a text transformation engine which is fed by text written in your favorite markup language, be that Markdown, Textile, or direct HTML. All content information are stored in standard text-files instead of a database, which increases the re-usability of the content and will ease every kind of data migration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text-transformation process uses the sweet, sweet &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Shopify/liquid/wiki&quot;&gt;Liquid Template engine&lt;/a&gt; and therefor you can tweak ANY output with ease to perfection. You also can configure how the site URLs look and of course what data gets displayed. There is no overhead in the html, lean&amp;amp;clean, it’s easy to extend even by non-programmers and delivers &lt;strong&gt;exact&lt;/strong&gt; results. All configurations and tweaks are done through editing text files, and the static web site is the final product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;get-it-working-&quot;&gt;Get it working …&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For everyone with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix-like&quot; title=&quot;Unix like OS on wikipedia&quot;&gt;Unix like Operating system&lt;/a&gt; or a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OS_X&quot; title=&quot;MacBook &amp;amp; Co.&quot;&gt;Mac OS X&lt;/a&gt; it is a task of a few minutes while drinking coffee and watching the installation progress to get everything up and ready. Just follow the instructions &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/installation/&quot; title=&quot;How to install Jekyll on your localhost&quot;&gt;in the Jekyll Documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt; ~ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;gem &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install &lt;/span&gt;jekyll&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Windows Warriors could consider for professional use an &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/?q=cool+and+free+operating+systems&quot;&gt;easier and cheaper Operating System&lt;/a&gt; and buy a PlayStation for gaming instead &lt;strong&gt;OR&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyll-windows.juthilo.com/&quot; title=&quot;Jekyll on Win OS&quot;&gt;make it work anyway&lt;/a&gt;. Once ready, we can start our project. Let’s call it FantasticContent.online. This will serve as fictional brand in the follow-ups, where we include this tool into a sophisticated software strategy, including version control as well as task and team management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;/&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; create new project &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'FantasticContent.online'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
~ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;jekyll new FantasticContent.online 
~ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;FantasticContent.online&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll will start a development server on your computer and also monitor all changes if you start it with the &lt;em&gt;serve&lt;/em&gt; parameter. This is very useful, so you can develop, test and preview the entire project in real time by opening &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;localhost:4000&lt;/a&gt; in your browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;~/FantasticContent.online &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-do-you-get&quot;&gt;What do you get?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our FanatasticContent.online folder should now contain a file-structure similar to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;├── _config.yml /&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; file contains site-wide configurations &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/ 
├── _drafts /&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; folder &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for &lt;/span&gt;un-published posts &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
| ├── unpublished-content-here.textile 
| └── versioning-works-great.markdown 
├── _includes /&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; re-usable snippets to generate footer, header, navigations ... &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
| ├── footer.html
| ├── header.html
| └── my_snippet.html 
├── _layouts /&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; the layout files &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
| ├── default.html 
| └── post.html 
├── _posts /&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; folder &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for &lt;/span&gt;all posts, categories and tags will map each to SEO friendly URLs&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; /
| └── 2015-11-19-faster-cheaper-safer.markdown
├── _data /&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; well-formated files&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;.yml, .cvs, .json&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; can hold additional site data &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
| └── members.yml
├── _sass /&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; yeah, sass is auto-compiled &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
| ├── _base.scss
| └── _layout.scss
├── _site /&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; contains the resulting compiled website &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
├── .jekyll-metadata /&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; hands off &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/
└── index.html /&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; the landing page &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other pages and folders, including new ones you create for images, contact or static content are simply copied by Jekyll into the &lt;em&gt;_site&lt;/em&gt; folder when generating the result. With access to the styles via sass, to the templates in &lt;em&gt;_layouts&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;_includes&lt;/em&gt; and to the data in  &lt;em&gt;_posts&lt;/em&gt; and in forms of folders and pages (as index.html), you have everything you need to get going. You can find more information in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/home/&quot; title=&quot;Browse Jekyll documentation ...&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; and feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Solomonic/theming.rasta_online&quot; title=&quot;Browse on github ...&quot;&gt;browse this blog’s more populated folder structure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important:&lt;/strong&gt; You NEVER want to make any changes directly in the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;_site&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; folder, everything in there is gone next time Jekyll regenerates the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;accessibility&quot;&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;layout&quot;&gt;Layout&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider the learning curve as very steep, so with very little experience a developer or designer is able to control any major aspect of the result. I’m fluent in several template languages for serveral CMS and haven’t found anything easier than the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Shopify/liquid/wiki&quot;&gt;Liquid Template engine&lt;/a&gt;. You can get by with very few coding skills as long as you can use these expressions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- build an index list of all posts--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Loop all posts --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  {% for post in site.posts %}
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- check condition: author available for ths post --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    {% if post.author %}
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;{{ post.url }}&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;{{ post.title }}&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    {% endif %}
  {% endfor %}
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- include re-usable snippets from _includes folder--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
{% include footer.html %}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;rapid-prototyping&quot;&gt;Rapid prototyping&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A developer with the understanding of any &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Object-oriented_programming&quot; title=&quot;Whats that?&quot;&gt;OOP&lt;/a&gt; will love &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/frontmatter/&quot; title=&quot;More in the documentation ...&quot;&gt;Frontmatter&lt;/a&gt;. You have 2 object-types by default: &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/posts/&quot; title=&quot;Learn more about posts ...&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/pages/&quot; title=&quot;Learn more about posts ...&quot;&gt;pages&lt;/a&gt;. Both have a &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/variables/&quot; title=&quot;Learn more about variables ...&quot;&gt;certain set of properties&lt;/a&gt; but can be extended with any new property just by adding it to the header of its text file. A default post head will look like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yaml&quot; data-lang=&quot;yaml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;faster, cheaper, safer&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;2015-11-19  00:00:00 +0700&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to add the author property, we just update it to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yaml&quot; data-lang=&quot;yaml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;faster, cheaper, safer&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;2015-11-19  00:00:00 +0700&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;author&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Jens Krause&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The testing and use of the new property in the layout is fairly simple&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;{% if post.author %}
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;{{ post.url }}&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;{{ post.author }}&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
{% endif %}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is not enough for your prototype, create your very own &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/collections/&quot; title=&quot;Learn more about custom types and collections ...&quot;&gt;content types with custom collections&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know about you, but I could build a wide range of applications with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;content-management&quot;&gt;Content management&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume we have a group of people responsible for the content of the website. We call them Editors, and we expect a low technical understanding. Their job is actually to create content and therefore to give life and blood to FantasticContent.Online. Visitors will be attracted by their work and not how lean the website is done or if it loads 0.2s faster or slower. We want to make the Editor’s job as easy as possible, so they can focus on the important things such as creating fantastic content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editors will require training to use any system, so instead of teaching the correct use of the CMS, it should be possible to teach them how to create markdown files and submit them into a prepared release cycle. There are markdown readers for any OS available and even &lt;a href=&quot;http://dillinger.io/&quot; title=&quot;Online markdown editor and reader ...&quot;&gt;good online tools&lt;/a&gt; which will support the content-team with the creation and updating of the files. I suggest that the understanding and ability to create those markdown files is more rapid and connected with fewer problems than handling content creation in any CMS. Most editors prefer to write offline anyway, so to ask for a well-formated file is very reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach can be very valuable especially in areas with slow and unreliable internet connections, since the content itself can be created offline and submitted by email, ftp or github as soon as the connection is available again, saving a lot of bandwidth in the process compared with the usual through-the-web creation of a traditional CMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;seo-and-marketing&quot;&gt;SEO and marketing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only worked for a very short time with static site generators so I’m not able to back up the following assumptions with real world data, but nevertheless we are able to make some qualified guesses for what we can expect with &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;earch &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;ngine &lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt;ptimization or, in better words, the indexing behavior. I don’t know exactly how a search engine indexes but could identify setups which work very well and have helped several of my customers to get the top-spot for the desired keywords. It never hurts, if&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we have good content (&lt;strong&gt;most important&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the URLs are well-formed &lt;em&gt;(bad: domain.com/index.php?id=99, good: domain.com/a-title-with-my-keywords)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we have a title and a description for each article in the HEAD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we provide a sitemap.tgz for the crawler bots&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we use valid HTML&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we use Webmaster tools to identfy and fix problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;meta keywords: I could not identify significant influence of them, but sure …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The URL magic is pretty good when the website is generated. It follows by default the form&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt; domain.com/CATEGORY1/CATEGORY2/YEAR/MONTH/DAY/TITLE-OF-POST.html &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post has the following Frontmatter variables set:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yaml&quot; data-lang=&quot;yaml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;faster, cheaper, safer&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;2015-11-19  00:00:00 +0700&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;author&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Jens Krause&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;categories&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;education software-development&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;tags&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;internet jekyll&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting URL and site structure is very SEO and readable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt; rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/11/19/faster-cheaper-safer.html &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also change the general URL mapping for all posts or set static &lt;em&gt;permalink&lt;/em&gt;s for special posts. We have every freedom we need, always just one Frontmatter variable away. Generating a sitemap is no problem, and every other identified positive SEO behavior seems very possible. Once set up, I believe it will have excellent indexing. I will start to collect data over the next weeks and include it in the follow-up SEO articles but my expectations are high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An popular approach to gather data about the vistor preferences and improve towards a better &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/forbestechcouncil/2015/11/19/good-ux-is-good-business-how-to-reap-its-benefits/&quot; title=&quot;Importance of UX on Forbes.com...&quot;&gt;user experience (UX)&lt;/a&gt; is split-testing, or &lt;strong&gt;A/B&lt;/strong&gt; campaigns. Usually is the same content presented with 2 different layouts, to see which is better received and lead to higher conversion rates. With the pre-compiled websites, it is very easy to implement those within one domain, just generate the same website 2 times with the different layouts, upload both sites in folder A and folder B and set your splitter algrorithm in front to do the splitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more interesting in this matter is how two or more domains with the very same content, same technical background and same SEO perform against each other with different layouts. Good &lt;strong&gt;U&lt;/strong&gt;ser E&lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;perience &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;esign (UXD) leads to better business and is essential to the financial success of a project. Big companies pay really big money for UX analysis and improvements. Believe me, I charged very well, and it was still always worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hosting-re-usability-and-security&quot;&gt;Hosting, re-usability and security&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the free hosting options with certain hosters, we gain a new freedom when it comes to content. It is in any case much easier to move to newer and faster servers if you just need to move your assets such as images and a bunch of html files. Hosting providers often offer very cheap services for the first year and increase their prices in the second and following years. This strategy works well because customers go for the low price first, while all their work in the CMS will be really hard to move to another location. This migration usually costs way more than a year of hosting, so they got you don’t they?
Nope, backup your images and upload them with the latest generated version of your project to the new server, done. Neither Layout nor Content are chained to the hoster anymore and you want them backed up anyway at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content data is now stored in well-formatted text files in an accessible central location instead of a local database. This is &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; useful for any kind of automated content re-use as in RSS, MailChimp Campaigns or new and more exciting possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t really need to worry about security aspects of your project. A static page cannot be hacked in the usual sense. A hacker could interfere with your ftp/sftp connection, but it is unlikely, and more importantly, you don’t need to worry that the CMS itself allows exploits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a professional, I see the approach of a pre-compiled CMS as superior to certain server-side applications. To be able to deploy different layout versions of the same content very cheap and very fast opens up a big field of scientific and business opportunities. My own personal prognosis, in November 2015, is that variations of pre-compiled CMS will take a huge market share as soon there is a free Windows GUI or Android App deploying automated lean websites into a free cloud hosting. Many server-side CMS &lt;strong&gt;just&lt;/strong&gt; show content the customer actually doesn’t want to touch. This seems like a lot of trouble since hosting, setup, and maintenance are way more expensive and the content is stuck in one database, which is pretty worthless without the CMS itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest drawback of this approach is clearly the missing real-time interaction. Nevertheless, it is very easy to include any kind of widgets for Ajax embeddings or something similar, so 3rd-party services can be utilized to overcome these disadvantages. A good example, for starters, is to use the facebook comments and likes to gain feedback, include a google form for an interactive site-search, and link to a MailChimp newsletter system and basic CRM. More details in the follow-up for the strategic setup of FantasticContent.Online, including amazing other tools we have available for free these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stay tuned …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 13:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/11/19/faster-cheaper-safer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/11/19/faster-cheaper-safer.html</guid>
        
        <category>internet</category>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        
        <category>education</category>
        
        <category>software-development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>CMS ... Wordpress, Joomla!, Drupal, Django, Typo3 or Plone</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Wordpress, Joomla!, Drupal, Django, Typo3 and Plone are some of the most common Content Management Systems (CMS) today, delivering millions of websites every day. &lt;strong&gt;But what is a CMS and what purpose does it serve?&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks to the open-source community, small projects, start-ups, or businesses with very limited budgets are able to get online with low-cost websites. This article explains some very basic concepts and what kind of issues you can expect when using any CMS…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an introduction into a series of articles, covering existing web-technologies and encouraging smarter, faster and cheaper solutions for the future. This article is meant to give a common ground for all kind of readers, so experience users will already know this.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;my-first-steps&quot;&gt;My first steps&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first website I ever made was in 2001 as a student of my local university. The task was to write a simple 5-page website, including navigation, some content with text, images, tables and a footer in the very bottom. Since I was a lazy dude, I was looking for the simplest way to achieve this and found a software application called “Microsoft Frontpage”, the first WYSIWYG Editor I ever came in contact with. By using it, I was able to build something decent-looking within 3 days, just by clicking around… and the Editor “translated” my actions into HTML &amp;amp; CSS code and generated my files. Ready to upload it to the internet, I felt like superman. I can make website!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-exactly-is-a-website&quot;&gt;What exactly is a website?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site never made it online, but I eventually understood what a website really is:
A HTML text-document (file with the ending .html), which may make its way to your browser through the internet OR is created by yourself on your own computer. One page is hardly a website, so we can connect a couple of the HTML files with each other through “links”. The styling is a set of rules how the browser should display certain parts of the HTML text. These rules are written down in another text-file with the ending .css and THIS is actually the part which can drive you nuts as a themer. The browser does all the work and finally translates all these text files into something useful, with color, images, videos, and many kinds of real-time interaction that we love so much and use every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-is-a-cms&quot;&gt;What is a CMS?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;ontent &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;anagement &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;ystems are an approach for web-applications to seperate Layout and Content. With layout I mean the CSS styles and the repeated HTML structures such as a logo, navigations, and a footer. On the other hand, we have a database storing all kinds of Content information like titles, descriptions, texts, creation and publishing dates, authorships, history, and positions in the page-tree for each article within a website. Youtube has its very own CMS. In a video page, you will find parts looking the same for each video. This is considered the Layout, while the video and its comments are the Content. The CMS provides the mechanisms to merge the Content information and Layout in order to produce one specific HTML page that is sent to my browser whenever I open a specific URL. There are scripts running on the server (your hosting), calculating in the most clever ways the resulting website that everybody is going to enjoy. We call these server-side applications, simply because the server has to work and compute for us to get the results. Server-side applications include all major CMS as well as everything cool on the internet allowing interaction. &lt;em&gt;So, a CMS is usually a server-side application, merging together Content stored in an online database with the Layout of a website.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;sounds-complicated-so-why-are-we-doing-this&quot;&gt;Sounds complicated, so why are we doing this?&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you have a website with 200 articles. When you decide to add a new article to the navigation, change one word in the footer, or simply update the copyright year you will need to update the layout of 200 HTML pages. This is very boring work because you need to fully focus all the time or you will mess up the website and it may takes hours until you get it perfect. Many web-developers made a living from updating static html pages and many, many still do to this day. Once you have 5,000, 50,000 or 500,000 articles on your website, static HTML pages become in fact un-manageable. With a CMS you usually log into a backend (often called admin panel or such), make your Layout updates exactly one time and all of your articles will display these changes immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;get-it-its-free&quot;&gt;Get it, it’s FREE!&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the open-source community, countless night-time hours of “moonshining” from geeks and nerds all around the world, we have a big varity of different free CMS solutions now and in many different Programming Languages such as PHP, Perl, Python or Ruby, serving the majority of websites on the internet today. They became very popular because the software itself is free and advertised as the easiest access into the online world. There is no need to learn HTML, that convinced at least all of my early customers.
&lt;strong&gt;All is great then, right?&lt;/strong&gt; Problem solved, case closed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;actually--problems-to-expect-from-your-cms&quot;&gt;Actually …. problems to expect from your CMS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;costs-its-not-free&quot;&gt;Costs: It’s not free!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software is free, but not the website. Every website needs a server to be stored on, whether it’s static HMTL or a sophisticated CMS. By nature, the sophisticated server-side appliocation needs more space, a database, and computing power to do its magic. The hosting costs vary widely between each CMS and are a major determining factor for how many people will use it. Wordpress as the absolute market leader (50%-60% of all CMS in use are Wordpress) often ships with very affordable hosting packages, while others like Plone (1%-2% market share) require about 10 times higher hosting costs. How often a CMS is used doesn’t prove its quality in any way, but it does demonstrate how well the costs and results are balanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, most website companies, web designers, themers, and web developers are specialized in &lt;strong&gt;one&lt;/strong&gt; CMS and will always recommend their own choice as the right one for every single project and customer.
&lt;em&gt;If your only tool is a hammer, every problem looks like a nail to you.&lt;/em&gt;
If a Wordpress professional discusses with the Plone professional, both can make valid points why their own product is superior to the other. Neither one will be right for every real world project and customer because the priorities and targets are different each time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real costs come into play when you hire a professional to do customizations, setup complicated environments, or implement non-standard features. Professionals can be found starting at $3/hour in developing countries such as India or charge up to $300+/hour in the first world, depending on the system, client and needed skillset. Every professional needs to find their balance between getting customers and getting paid. I usually recommend my students to become a skilled specialist with less competion and therefore charge higher hourly rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ease-of-use&quot;&gt;Ease of use&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many clients seems to be disappointed when they realize that their new website-system is way more complicated than they expected. If you are the reseller of a CMS, you will need to deal with the bugs or missing features of the product for your client. A word of warning: a customer who is not interested in the techie side and doesn’t want to deal with HTML is very likely not very keen on learning to handle the CMS and find the ways around the pitfalls. This customer will always have the feeling that workflows are too complicated, because they would rather put their energy into business instead of managing the technical website tasks. The more capable an application is, the more complex it gets, and the chances are higher for bugs, errors and confusion. &lt;strong&gt;There is always a need for specialists.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;speed&quot;&gt;Speed&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All server-side applications will need a some time to analyze your request, generate your HTML reponse page and send it back to you. The weaker the hosting server is, the longer it will take until the CMS page finally appears. There are approaches for every system to improve speed by more efficient algorithms, advanced caching setups and resource compressions, but no matter what a CMS implements, it will be &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; slower then a correct static HTML website with comparable content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what? My website is slower, does this make a difference?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That depends on your goals. &lt;a href=&quot;http://tools.pingdom.com/fpt/#!/wTly2&quot;&gt;This article was tested with 272ms loading time&lt;/a&gt;, but results always vary over time and with location. I would expect a CMS in a standard setup to be at least 1s slower, way more with some of them. Studies show that website visitors clearly recognize the increase of speed by 0.1s and will prefer and return more often to the faster websites. Clever specialists can modify the CMS with optimizations, minimizations, and setups to obtain a speed very close to a static HTML page, but it requires big efforts and still will be slower. You can compare this basic dilemma with two neighbors at Halloween who want to give out candy as fast as possible. One is standing right behind the door with candy in their hand waiting, while the other has to grab it from the kitchen first. Who will win?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wordpress and its fellow CMS are valuable tools in creating websites and publishing content. They serve most of the world’s websites and have proved themselves over and over again. Nevertheless, there is not one CMS that is the best tool for every task and all of them have plenty of built-in disadvantages. Through their complexity they force people to specialize on one or very few systems, which actually is a disadvantage to the common customer. The Joomla! guy won’t send customers to Drupal and would rather find an alternative approach using his specialty. So if a customer doesn’t know which CMS is the best choice in their situation or who to contact, it seems mere luck what they are getting in the end, depending on who they asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the follow-up article, I want to shed some light on a different professional approach for low-cost, high-speed web projects, following best pratices, and it may end up adding a new tool to your digital toolbox. Stay tuned until we dive a little into pre-compiled websites and what they can offer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 13:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/11/17/cms-wordpress-joomla-drupal-django-typo3-plone.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rasta.online/education/software-development/2015/11/17/cms-wordpress-joomla-drupal-django-typo3-plone.html</guid>
        
        <category>internet</category>
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        
        <category>education</category>
        
        <category>software-development</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
